Guide to the Men's Student Government Association Records, 1925-1969
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Men's Student Government Association records 1925-1969
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Men's Student Government Association.
2.5 Linear Feet 2500 Items
The Men's Student Government Association (MSGA) evolved from student councils in the early 1930s at Duke University's Trinity College. The MSGA was supplanted by the Associated Students of Duke University in 1968. In 1993, the Associated Students of Duke University became known as Student Government Association.
Types of material include minutes, committee reports, correspondence, financial records, newsletters, election records (including records of the disputed 1952 election), constitutions, and resolutions. Materials range in date from 1925 to 1969.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Provenance
The Men's Student Government Association Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973 and 1986.
Historical Note
The Men's Student Government Association (MSGA) evolved from student councils in the early 1930s at Duke University's Trinity College. In April 1945, the Engineer's Student Government Association merged with the Trinity College Student Government Association to form the Men's Student Government Association. The MSGA created policies governing students, reviewed student group charters, and represented student interests to faculty and administration.
The Men's Student Government Association debated over the administration of the Duke University traditions test to freshmen (and required freshmen caps called dinks), the organization of the Committee on Freshmen Rules and Traditions, and measures taken when students failed the traditions exam. Meetings from the 1940s through the late 1960s included discussions about parking registration, aid for Hungarian students, alcohol use on campus, the issue of segregated seating in Wallace Wade Stadium, integration, and disciplinary actions. Meetings of the 1960s especially reflected student involvement in social issues like the Vietnam War, segregation in the Wallace Wade Stadium, and co-educational housing.
The Student-Faculty Advisory Committee (SFAC), a subcommittee of the MSGA, was composed of presidents of student groups, faculty, and administration. Meetings of the elite SFAC were closed to non-SFAC members, much to the protest of other students. Issues discussed at SFAC meetings significantly impacted policies at Duke University. The committee focused on regulation of illegal drugs, campus political organizations, campus traditions, cheating, the coordinate college system, and the Pickets and Protests Policy. The SFAC was most likely associated with the Order of Red Friars, a secret society of administrators, faculty, and students at Duke University.
The MSGA was supplanted by the Associated Students of Duke University in 1968. In 1993, the Associated Students of Duke University became known as Student Government Association.
Collection Overview
The collection cinludes the minutes, reports and other records of the Student-Faculty-Advisory Committee (SFAC). The SFAC was a subcommittee of the MSGA, created to discuss matters of mutual concern to students, faculty, and the administration (circa 1961-1969). It also includes MSGA minutes, committee reports, correspondence, financial records, newsletters, election records (including records of the disputed 1952 election), constitutions, and resolutions. Major subjects include Duke University, student government, the Men's Student Government Association, history of the Associated Students of Duke University, history of the Student Government Association, policy revision, administration and student relations, alcohol use on campus, segregation, illegal drug use, political activity, origins of the football game Victory Bell, campus traditions, college freshmen, and cheating. Contains restricted materials. Materials range in date from 1925 to 1969.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Men's Student Government Association
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Duke University. Associated Students of Duke University
Duke University. Men's Student Government Association. Student Faculty Advisory Committee
Duke University -- Students -- Political activity
Duke University -- Students -- Attitudes
Cheating (Education).
College freshmen -- North Carolina -- Durham
College students -- Alcohol use
College students -- Drug use
Related Material
Associated Students of Duke University Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library/University Archives, Duke University
Women's Student Government Association Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library/University Archives, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Minutes and correspondence, 1940-1967
  Contains correspondence of the Men's Student Government Association from other Duke University departments, student groups, and community organizations. Minutes and correspondence are grouped together in many files. Contains restricted materials.
  - Minutes,1940-1942 RESTRICTED (Box 1)
  - Minutes and correspondence, 1931-1942
  - Minutes and correspondence, 1945-1946
  - Minutes, 1945 December 6 and 1946 January 23 RESTRICTED
  - Minutes and Social Committee report, 1946-1947
  - Memorandum, 1947 November 6 RESTRICTED
  - Minutes and correspondence, 1947-1948
  - Minutes and correspondence, 1948-1949
  - Minutes, 1950-1955
  - Minutes, 1955-1956
  - Minutes, 1956-1957
  - Minutes, 1960-1962
  - Minutes, 1963-1964
  - Minutes, 1964-1967
  - Correspondence, 1960-1966
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967
- Proposals and recommendations, 1951-1969
  Includes proposals and recommendations aimed at solving problems on campus faced by students. Proposals usually include background information, research, surveys, and plans for action. Some MSGA proposals concerned long lines in the bookstore, increasing the frequency of the Duke Chronicle so that it could cover more events, establishing a central "ride board," employing housekeepers on Saturdays, and updating the honor code. Ordered by date.
  - Proposals and recommendations, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - New acts passed, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions passed, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1961-1967, undated (Box 1)
- Elections, 1952, 1960
  Includes materials pertaining to the 1952 and 1960 elections. The 1952 election was widely disputed due to party pressure and some allegedly underhanded tactics. Accounts of bystanders and participants are included. Ordered by date.
  - Election: eyewitness accounts, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Election: fliers, announcements, general publicity materials, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Election: ballots, results, rules, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Inaugurations, 1957-1965 (Box 1)
- General governance, 1925-1968
  Contains the constitutions and bylaws of the Men's Student Government Association, financial materials and an operating manual. The varying dates of constitutions reflect the MSGA's duties and influence on campus. Student groups wishing to be formally recognized at Duke University, and apply for funding from the student government, submitted charters to the MSGA for approval. Ordered by date.
  - MSGA constitution and bylaws, 1925, 1954-1967 (Box 1)
  - MSGA constitution and bylaws, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - West Campus Student Government Association, proposed constitutions, circa 1960s (Box 1)
  - Student groups, charters and constitutions, circa 1960s (Box 1)
  - Financial materials, 1955-1968 (Box 1)
  - President's Operating Procedure Manual, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
- Projects and issues, other materials 1962-1977
  Contains correspondence, short writings, and drafts of policies regarding certain issues on campus during the 1960s. The memorabilia file contains a handmade invitation to an Alumni Affairs Luncheon. Ordered by date. Some items came from general oversize collection box 3 and were transferred to a legal Hollinger box (box 2) on April 18, 2007.
  - Exterior publicity ban, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Freshman government, 1961-1967 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Board and Court of Appeals, 1961-1966 (Box 2)
  - Parking and Traffic, 1963-1966
  - Trust Fund, 1966
  - Student Life, 1960-1966, 1977
  - Tutorial projects, 1965
  - YMCA, 1960-1961
  - Newsletters, 1962-1963
  - Fliers, 1951, undated
  - Memorabilia, 1963
  - Miscellaneous Documents, Memoranda, 1952-1965 (removed from oversize collection)
  - C.O.R.E. Constitution, undated (removed from oversize collection)
  - Reports and Newsletters, 1955-1966 (removed from oversize collection)
- Student-Faculty-Advisory Committee (SFAC), 1963-1968
  Contains materials relating to the Student-Faculty-Advisory Committee. The general issue files contain materials on the honor system, segregation, dormitory room privacy, recruiting policies of the University, alcohol use, illegal drugs on campus, and firearms on campus. Correspondence contains an undated flier to a Red Friars event. Materials were transferred to separate legal-sized Hollinger box on April 18, 2007.
  - Minutes and agendas, 1963-1966 (Box 3)
  - Minutes and agendas, 1966-1967
  - Minutes and agendas, 1968
  - General organization, constitutions, and purpose, 1962-1968
  - Brief chronology of past deliberations, 1962-1967
  - SFAC committees and discussion of student participation on committees, circa 1967
  - General issues, proposals and reports, circa 1963-1968
  - Picketing and protest issue, proposals and reports, circa 1968
  - Correspondence, 1964-1967, undated